Coach: Clip it, or something.
Natalie Spiska: Sounds good.
Natalie Spiska: Alright.
Coach: You could share it with your coach.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, sounds good.
Natalie Spiska: I'll let him know. So, jumping right into it, if you could briefly explain what technology your golf program uses right now, including any sort of wearable technology or stats website?
Coach: Yeah, I mean, currently we have two Trackman simulators, and we use the TrackMan outside for, obviously, like, launch.
Coach: Monitor and distance control.
Coach: We're using CLIP for statistics, like, You know, just course data.
Coach: And… I mean, I think that's all we're using right now. We are…
Coach: We are in the process of building a new building that that,
Coach: you know, I think… I think it's just trying to find the right technology that's utilized. You know, sometimes, like, we've had a sand putt lab, but once you use it once or twice.
Coach: You kind of get bored with it and don't use it a lot, you know, so it's…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: I think just finding the bang for the buck that's… Useful.
Natalie Spiska: And I know that you guys have, obviously, a men's and women's team. Is there any difference in the technology between the teams, or is it, like, both teams use the track men's?
Coach: No, we are everything.
Natalie Spiska: Okay.
Coach: Actually, I purchased most of it, the men's coach wonders why we get this stuff, but then after.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: He goes, oh, that was good.
Natalie Spiska: I see.
Natalie Spiska: How would you say the use of technology in your program has changed over the last few years?
Coach: I think… Well, I think, you know, it's just gotten better with, understanding the data, and…
Coach: You know, or even able to just…
Coach: I guess you can quantitate… I think it helps with quality of practice rather than quantity. I mean, I think in the old days, without the track, man, you're just hitting balls, and you think you know what you're doing, but…
Coach: You know, it uncovers a level of, like, you know, spin rates or launch angles that…
Coach: you know, you're like, why can't I hit this driver? And then you find out that, you know, the shaft is wrong, and the spin's wrong, and it's not your swing, so…
Coach: I think it's actually… it just makes the practice more of a quality…
Coach: Return, if you know what you're doing, and then…
Coach: You know, I also think the problem in golf, I mean, I've been a golf pro for 30 years, besides being a coach, is that…
Coach: you know, I think it fast-tracks you to the answers, and then also, like, helps you understand the standards of what you need to do, rather than
Coach: you know, I think golf, so much we focus on what's going wrong, rather than trying to figure out what's going right, and how do we get back to that.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I definitely agree. I think, especially with the rise of technology, of understanding how to use it, that's definitely, like, super important to know, to actually be able to use it in a good way.
Natalie Spiska: Are there any…
Coach: Most of the people that don't… most of the people that don't like to use the technology, I don't think, understand it.
Coach: That's why it's a little overwhelming.
Coach: But even right now, like, I don't know, we… I just found the Performance Center, I don't know if you guys use that already, or if you have TrackMan, but…
Coach: The performance center's, like, on track land. It basically has tee shots and approach shots, and it actually has greens and different shapes, so it can help you visualize the actual shot.
Coach: And then… Yeah, I've solved, yeah. Rather than just hit my driver, and I hit it 220 with 240 rolled, or…
Coach: So… You gotta understand it, I think, is the end of the day, is the problem.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I definitely agree. With Performance Center as well. That was, like, a new feature I think they added a while ago. Well, maybe, like, last month or something, but I was also looking at them, like, oh, it's pretty cool now that you can hit, like, specifically tee shots as well.
Coach: Yeah, or that works on maybe your, you know, what you don't work at, or… but you're just not pounding balls, I think it engages you. I mean, our tracking rep was here this week.
Natalie Spiska: Can you hear me? I think you lost some connection.
Natalie Spiska: Hello?
Coach: Can you hear me?
Coach: Yeah, I had a call come in, I tried to decline it, I don't know if that interrupted.
Natalie Spiska: Okay, that's okay. You, you just kind of went away for a few seconds, but you're back.
Coach: Oh, no, I was just saying that, like, I think the tour players, they were saying, use it on the range, even outside with the Performance Center, but I think it just makes your practice more engaging, rather than…
Coach: you know, just hitting and getting numbers, is what I…
Coach: Cool.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I definitely agree. Are there any particular skill areas where you think the technology's made the biggest impact? Like, ball striking, short game, putting…
Coach: I mean, I think it definitely even club fitting or ball striking, I mean, you can find out the spin rates, like, with drivers.
Coach: you know, or even, like, just this week, I mean, I… you know, we went through a few bags, a couple girls had, say, like, one or two odd clubs, and I took their clubs down and had the loft and lies checked, and it took… turned around that, you know.
Coach: One of their lie angles was off by, like, 3 degrees, and, you know, we bent it to…
Coach: Where it needed to be in the sequence, and then we went back on the track, man, and…
Coach: You know, the numbers are falling back into place.
Coach: So, I mean, I think she played the whole fall season like that, to be honest.
Coach: She's like, my 9-iron's weird, and it was like, she placed 2 degrees flat, and the club was 2 degrees up.
Coach: So the law is not…
Coach: I mean, I think the technology today, like, gets away from the naked eye and gives you the details of what's going on.
Coach: So instead of us guess… it takes the guesswork out of all this, and then… I think once you're out there playing…
Coach: You just have to trust the process, and know that, you know, your clubs are set up right, and the clubs go the right distance, and…
Coach: You know, even right now, the biggest thing we're doing is just gappings. You know, figuring out how far the gaps are, where your weaknesses are, and where the carry is, so that when we get out on the courses, we can play.
Coach: beat [University] that, again, you know, we're just stirring the pot, and
Coach: you know, it just helps you play better. I think when you get on the course, you just want to think less, so, like, I mean, I think your practice time gives you the time to get in the dirt and get the details, and then when you go on the course, you're kind of already dialed in, you know what…
Coach: Your clubs can do, and how the machine can run.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I think especially, obviously, you guys are much more up north than we are, so I'm sure it's just as cold, but yeah, gapping on the track minutes are super important, I feel like, to actually figure out how far your ball's gonna go before you can get down to someplace like Florida.
Natalie Spiska: So…
Coach: I think even the putting stuff helps, I mean, you can see the ball roll, or bounce, and…
Coach: you know, there's so many different things, and I think then they're only gonna get better and better, I mean…
Coach: I hate to say, when the coaches used to play, I mean, we didn't have rangefinders, you didn't have, you know.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, whole new world.
Coach: But, you know, you guys don't know how to hit field shots. You'd be, like, 20 yards off, you're shooting at 20 yards. Can't you just see that it's right there? Like…
Coach: Anyways…
Natalie Spiska: Always had to make sure, you know?
Coach: Yeah, right.
Natalie Spiska: Have you noticed any improvements in your team since implementing, like, the performance technology?
Coach: I don't know, I guess that's a good question, I mean,
Coach: I don't know, we keep getting better.
Natalie Spiska: If I ask, when did you get your track men's? Was that a few years ago, or…
Coach: Yeah, we've had them for a few years, so…
Coach: I mean, I think you… I guess it would… I look at it the other way, it's not so much that the tee gotten better, I think that, like, junior golf, that you guys have grown up with that, so…
Natalie Spiska: You know, the…
Coach: I think the data and the technology
Coach: you know, I think it also just helps even, like, with everyone's teachers or different far away. I mean, we can just send you numbers to…
Coach: You know, it's like the…
Coach: I think technology's helped even just… I mean, we're Zooming right now, like, you know, I'm just saying, like, we take it for granted, but, like, you know, the resources to be able to…
Coach: are definitely making, like, everything better. I mean, whether I can work with your coach at home.
Coach: Or, you know, we can just look at numbers and…
Coach: I don't know, I think you gotta stay with the times. I mean, if you're not utilizing technology, you're like…
Coach: You're a dinosaur, and you're kind of falling behind.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Natalie Spiska: I think, yeah, definitely, especially with so much more technology coming out as well, like SportsBox AI, I don't know if you saw that or not, like, it's an app that basically takes your swing and recreates it in 3D space, and there's just a whole bunch of crazy things that are coming out that, yeah, if you're not utilizing it, you're definitely falling behind.
Coach: I mean, you should… I don't know how much your project is, I mean, you know that was created by a Yale grad that played golf, right? Yeah.
Natalie Spiska: I did see that, yeah. I follow her on LinkedIn.
Coach: Good.
Coach: No, I mean, but also, you know, the hard part is, I've seen it, I understand it, but…
Coach: I mean, I think that… that's a pretty cool product, but, you know, even at the PGA show every year, I mean, I think that's the hard part, is they… some people come up with this technology, and is it… is it rea… is it sizzle, or is it real?
Coach: Meaning, like, the… the…
Coach: That… that thing, I think, is real, but you know what I'm saying? Some people are selling the sizzle, and…
Coach: Some people are… You know, what's really moving the game forward?
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, definitely. Have you seen any differences in how athletes on your team respond to the technology? Like, some people benefit more from it, or, like, a certain personality fits the technology better?
Coach: Yeah, I mean, I think it's all learning style. You know, like, if…
Coach: if you can't grasp the 3D, or if you… I mean, it's also like some players are technical, and some players are field.
Coach: Like, some players don't even want to know, like… I'm like, oh, you need a lighter shaft, you need this, like…
Coach: you know, I think it's just how your brain works and your learning style, so… I mean, some players…
Coach: You know, we also call it track man fever, that, you know, they get stuck in the numbers and they forget how to play.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: I mean, I think the technology's good for building the foundation and building the…
Coach: Operate, you know, like, understanding your clubs, but at some point, you just have to play.
Coach: So, you know, some players, yeah, it's great. If you're an analytical mind, I mean, I think being at Dartmouth here, you know, we're very intelligent, but I lead the nation in questions. Everything's why, coach? Why? And… or sometimes you get that flyer that…
Coach: you know, like, Coach, I hit my seminary and it went 180, that's not… again, no kidding, just throw it out. Like, you… you can't take every shot literal, it's… it's more of a trend.
Coach: But it also comes down to the person.
Natalie Spiska: Are there any technologies that you've tried to use and ended up not using it or implementing it? And, like, what was the reason if that did happen?
Coach: Well, yeah, I mean, I would say, like, we had the Sam Putt Lab for a little bit, and I think…
Coach: That was good to set the standard, but… I think it got boring.
Coach: You know, like.
Coach: you know… And I've even talked to some putting experts that…
Coach: you know, your path is your path. It's not really, like…
Coach: I think your putting stroke, you're not trying to optimize it where it's textbook and it has to be square to square, like, you know, you might have your own natural path, and you just have to understand how it works.
Natalie Spiska: Like, you know, some people might take it inside and shove it.
Coach: But you hit it straight, so, you know, you have to understand when…
Coach: Does it need to be text point, or where is that, like, more like your fingerprint?
Coach: And you do your own style, so I guess… I mean, I… I guess I'm also a learner, there, you know, I'm… I'm not afraid to try new stuff, but you have to evaluate each product and see if it works for you.
Natalie Spiska: I know we had the sand putt lap for a while as well. I helped set it up, and yeah, once I did the first run-through, it's kind of like, okay, well, there's games on it that you could play, but those aren't really, like, helpful. So I was like, well, not too much you can really do once you get those.
Coach: Yeah, but I think that's the cool thing with technology, is I think that some of these companies are starting to… like, PuttView…
Coach: I think it's a cool new one that, you know, changes the different tracks, and… you know, you gotta play them more like games. I mean, I think the Sam Putt Lab is also more just…
Coach: I mean, I talked to the [University] coach about it, that, you know, if you use it, like, monthly, it's more to just make sure that you're on the right track and things are working the right way, but after a while, if it's not on or game-oriented, you're like, this is boring.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Natalie Spiska: This is a little bit…
Natalie Spiska: Out of, like, the last few topics, but do you worry about the privacy of your athletes when it comes to any of the technologies discussed?
Coach: The privacy?
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, because I know for wearable technologies, that's a big issue now as well, because a lot of these athletes' data are kind of just being taken, but I guess in the sense of TrackMan and, like, PuttFute, there's not exactly, like, your biometrics being scanned on there or not.
Coach: Yeah, I think, well…
Coach: I don't know, are you worried about personal data being shared? Is that what you're worried about?
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: I don't know.
Coach: I mean, at some point, I think you gotta be realistic. I mean, we're talking about your golf swing, we're not talking about, like, your fingerprint, or your…
Coach: DNA.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: I mean, but I mean, obviously, maybe the simple answer is if someone feels uncomfortable, you can't make them do it.
Coach: But then as a coach, you're also not putting someone in a…
Coach: you know, you're not trying to invade their privacy, I mean, like, come on.
Natalie Spiska: That's good.
Coach: It's like taking your picture at the airport on your ID. Is that really invading your privacy? You might have a debate that it is, but do you want to get on the plane?
Coach: I mean, if you're looking… first of all, I mean, if you're just collecting data and using it for swing path, or…
Coach: Patterns, and it's not like…
Coach: oh, Natalie did this. I mean, you're not calling someone out, I mean, if it's just a pattern…
Coach: you know… I mean, I unders… I don't know, I think it's a trick question.
Coach: Yeah, but you're gonna find some people might, you know, I don't know, I'm a pretty open guy, though, you know, an open coach, like, you're… talk about a sport trying to get better, we're not trying to infringe on…
Coach: I mean, that's up there, like, should you post your score if you play bad?
Natalie Spiska: We don't want to stress.
Coach: Yep.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, that's a good point.
Coach: I think out of the box sometimes.
Natalie Spiska: What types of performance tools or insights do you wish existed but don't yet? Or if you can't think of anything, is there any sort of technology you wish you could get for your program?
Coach: If you could create something that could measure people's self-confidence.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah? Interesting.
Coach: Or belief in themselves.
Coach: Excellent.
Natalie Spiska: How do you feel like that would impact players on the course? Like, to see if you're… even if you're performing work?
Coach: I think so. No, I mean, I'm kidding, I'm saying I think sometimes you get worried about…
Coach: your numbers, or they know what it is, but I'm saying, at the end of the day, I mean…
Coach: You could know all your numbers, but if you don't trust your swing, or trust the distances, or trust yourself, like…
Coach: you know, I don't know, I am a big mental code.
Natalie Spiska: Can you hear me? I can't hear you right now.
Natalie Spiska: Hello?
Natalie Spiska: I can't hear you, can you hear me?
Natalie Spiska: Okay. I don't think I can hear you, unfortunately.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I still can't hear you.
Natalie Spiska: Maybe, try leaving and reconnecting again?
Coach: Hello?
Natalie Spiska: Oh, I can hear you now.
Coach: That better, sir. I had a phone call come in, I don't know how I can turn that off, but…
Coach: Oh, they're hot.
Natalie Spiska: That's all good. I only have, two more questions left anyways, so…
Coach: Perfect.
Natalie Spiska: What role do you see technology playing in collegiate golf in, like, in the future, and do you think it'll change the recruiting process in any way?
Coach: Yeah, I mean, I think… I think data's always getting better, and…
Coach: I mean, even, I don't know if you've even looked at… I don't know how much it's technology, but, like, at that golf performance down in [City], I don't know if the coach has taken you there, they have that PDI stuff.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: Like, player development, but… Man, I think technology's always…
Coach: getting better, and I think they're finding different ways to measure things that…
Coach: I would think in the future, yeah, I mean, it's even, like, whether it's your stroke differential, or all these different rankings, and…
Coach: I mean, I would think technology has to get better and keep improving, it's just they're rewriting the codes to…
Coach: analyze the data, right? That's… did you play on a tough golf course? I mean, I think…
Coach: you know, I think the USGA is even doing it now, how, like, they changed the rating…
Coach: I don't… I think I'm saying this right, but you could correct me, or you should ask him, it's like.
Coach: Like, even the membership handicap is being variable by the day.
Coach: You know, like… Yeah.
Coach: If it's a… well, and I think even over, like, in Scotland, they almost, like…
Coach: I want to say, like, they changed the difficulty of the course per day, because, you know, if you're… I mean, your scoring average in a rainy and windy day is not going to be the same as if it's summer and clear and…
Coach: You know, so I think it's more like…
Coach: it against the competition of that day, does that make sense? Like…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, that definitely does.
Coach: So, I mean, I think technology definitely has to get better. I mean, if it wasn't, why would you be doing this project?
Coach: And if you're not thinking the techno… I mean, I think that's…
Coach: I think what's hard with golf is it's just, like, an old sport that's been around forever, but now…
Coach: you know, that's why I think everyone hits it so far and plays so well. I mean, I think you gotta… you gotta start… everyone complains about the ball, but I think you gotta make the drivers smaller.
Coach: I mean, the heads are too big, that's why you hit it so… waiting so long?
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Natalie Spiska: I definitely, I've kept on to my Callaway driver for a good 6 years now, just because I… I don't like the bigger heads, I want it to stay small, so I definitely agree with you on that.
Coach: Yeah, but I think you almost need to try a new one. I think these faces and the weighting, it's surprising that you're not changing yourself, but it just keeps getting further.
Natalie Spiska: I mean, I think the shaft on your driver's the most important piece, because it just doesn't matter what's at the end of the club head if you deliver it wrong.
Coach: Yeah. So keep the same shaft, but just try a new head.
Natalie Spiska: And my final question, overall, would you say that technology has had a positive or negative impact on your program?
Coach: Oh, totally positive. I mean, it's like… I think it's just streamlining or fast-tracking it, like, instead of…
Coach: you know, the data is… makes it easy to show even a player, like, this is what you're doing, this is why it's going there, like, I think it gives you the answers to the test.
Natalie Spiska: That sounds good.
Coach: But I think you gotta be a little bit of an expert, like, I think what's hard is, like, even the trackman.
Coach: not put it on him, but I don't… I doubt your coach knows about path and angle of attack, you know, like… you know, we break [Coach]
Natalie Spiska: I know somewhat, he's learning.
Coach: He's learning, yeah, he's trying to put the key in the car, it's a push-button start, you know?
Coach: But, don't worry, I know your coach well, you can tell I'm breaking his jobs.
Natalie Spiska: No worries. I told him that I was interviewing you today, and he got very excited.